Guide to the James Welch Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
James Welch papers
1889-2006
1960-2003
YCAL MSS 248
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
27.22
(54 boxes)
The James Welch Papers contain manuscripts, correspondence, and personal papers documenting the life and work of author James Welch. James Welch is well known for his fiction dealing with the histories and experiences of Native Americans, and the drafts of manuscripts, for novels and other works, together with correspondence and secondary literature, make the Welch papers a valuable resource for research in literary, American, and Native American studies.
Welch, James, 1940-2003
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Ken Lopez on various funds, 1994-2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Surrogates of all audio recordings are available within the collection. Preservation photocopies and computer printouts have been substituted in the main files for reference use.
Box 55 (computer disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
JAMES WELCH (1940-2003)
James Welch was a poet, novelist, and teacher. Born on the Blackfeet Indian Reservation in Browning, Montana, with Blackfeet and Gros Ventres ancestry, Welch drew upon the histories and experiences of Native Americans in his literary work. His publications include collections of poetry, novels, and nonfiction. Works include Riding the Earthboy 40 (1971), Fools Crow (1986), The Heartsong of Charging Elk (2000), and Killing Custer: The Battle of the Little Bighorn and the Fate of the Plains Indians (1994).
Summary information on James Welch is available in the standard print and online biographical resources.
The following chronology provides dates for key events and
publications:
1940 born in Browning, Montana
1954-1958 lives in Minneapolis, Minnesota
1958 graduates from Washburn High School, Minneapolis, Minnesota
1959 attends University of Minnesota
1961-1962 attends Northern Montana College, Havre, Montana
1962-1968 attends University of Montana, Missoula
1968 marries Lois Monk
1969 awarded National Endowment for the Arts grant
1971 publication of Riding the Earthboy 40
1972-1973 travels in Greece
1974 publication of Winter in the Blood
1977 teaches at University of Washington
1979 publication of The Death of Jim Loney
1981 appointment at University of Washington
1986 publication of Fools Crow
1986 publication of The Reak West Marginal Way: A Poet's Autobiography
by Richard Hugo (ed.)
1990 publication of The Indian Lawyer
1994 publication of Killing Custer
2000 publication of The Heartsong of Charging Elk
2003 August 4, dies in Missoula, Montana
Scope and Contents
The James Welch Papers consist of manuscripts, correspondence, and personal papers documenting the life and work of author James Welch. James Welch is well known for his fiction dealing with the histories and experiences of Native Americans, and the drafts of manuscripts, for novels and other works, together with correspondence and secondary literature, make the Welch papers a valuable resource for research in literary, American, and Native American studies. The collection spans the years 1889 to 2006, with the bulk of the collection dating from the early 1960s to 2003.
The collection is housed in 55 boxes and organized into four series: Writings of James Welch, Writings of Others, Correspondence, and Personal Papers. Boxes 50-55 contain Oversize and Restricted Fragile material.
Series I, Writings of James Welch, housed in boxes 1-32, is organized into six subseries: Articles and Essays, Lectures and Speeches, Novels, Poetry, Short Fiction, and Other Writings. The series features drafts and proofs for each of Welch's five novels, his collection of poems, and his nonfiction book on the Battle of Little Bighorn.
The Articles and Essays subseries, housed in box 1, includes autobiographical and critical writings. Autobiographical writings deal with Welch's writing history, his identity as a Native American author, and his experience as a Native American in the U.S. in the latter half of the 20th century. Other writings in this subseries include book reviews, tributes, including one to his teacher Richard Hugo, and prefatory and introductory essays on such subjects as Native American and regional literature, the Blackfeet, and life in Montana.
The Lectures and Speeches subseries, also housed in box 1, includes commencement and graduation speeches, introductions, and discussions of Native American literature and history. In the lecture entitled "Native American Renaissance," for example, Welch discusses the work of several other Native American authors, including N. Scott Momaday, Leslie Silko, Joy Harjo, Louise Erdrich, and Sherman Alexie.
The Novels subseries, housed in boxes 1-22, contains drafts, proofs, and other materials for Welch's five novels. In addition to computer printouts and typescript drafts of manuscripts, many of which are corrected, there are also drafts in electronic form. The Welch papers include twenty-seven computer disks, most of which contain files for drafts and research notes relating to particular books. There are fifteen disks, for example, containing drafts for The Heartsong of Charging Elk. In this case, the synopsis and background material, multiple paper and electronic drafts, setting copies, and publicity document the evolution of this text and Welch's writing method.
The Poetry subseries, housed in boxes 23-27, includes drafts and proofs for Welch's collection, Riding the Earthboy 40 (1971), as well as drafts for individual poems. The individual poems, which are arranged alphabetically by title, contain multiple drafts, in holograph and typescript. Many poems date from 1966 to 1968, when Welch was a graduate student at the University of Montana (Missoula), and thus represent early literary efforts.
Other Writings, housed in boxes 28-32, consists of material relating to Welch's nonfiction work, entitled Killing Custer, including a book proposal, background material and notes, drafts, proofs, publicity, and film project notes.
Drafts of writings in electronic form are identified in the box and folder list and include folder notes identifying the disk number and label. The files on the disks were either copied or migrated, and reference copies of the files are available on CDs, which may be viewed on laptops in the library's Reading Room. The original disks are stored in Restricted Fragile.
One computer disk in the collection contains files for outgoing letters and articles. The articles were printed onto copyright paper and arranged alphabetically by title for reference use.
Scattered drafts and copies of writings can also be found as enclosures in Series III. Correspondence and among the school materials in Series IV. Personal Papers.
Series II, Writings of Others, housed in boxes 33-34, is organized into two subseries: Writings of Others on James Welch and Other Writings. Writings on Welch include published articles and interviews, and student papers, theses, and dissertations. The articles, present in both English and French, include book reviews and discussions of Welch's work, some in the context of Native American literature. Noteworthy among the articles is a special issue of Studies in American Indian Literatures (2006) devoted to Welch. The theses and dissertations include three book-length studies on Welch and a German translation of Fools Crow. Writings of others can also be found as enclosures in Series III. Correspondence. These writings are identified in folder notes.
Series III, Correspondence, housed in boxes 35-46, is arranged alphabetically by last name. The correspondence consists chiefly of incoming personal and professional correspondence, though drafts and computer printouts of outgoing letters are also present. There are incoming letters from writers, editors, publishers, literary scholars and critics, and cultural organizations. The correspondence features letters from Western and Native American writers, as well as writers who settled in Montana, and scholars of Native American literature. These correspondents include Kim Barnes, Ralph Beer, LaVerne Harrell Clark, Joy Harjo, Kent Haruf, Patricia Henley, Alvin Josephy, Steven Krauzer, Arnold Krupat, Cyra McFadden, and N. Scott Momaday. There are also letters from Frederick Busch, Sharon Butala, Annie Dillard, Peter Matthiessen, Ann Patchett, and Gary Snyder.
One computer disk in the collection contains over 100 outgoing letters. These letters were printed onto copyright paper and arranged in the correspondence files for reference use. Reference copies of electronic files are available on CDs and may be viewed on laptops in the library's Reading Room.
Enclosures, such as drafts and copies of writings, photographs, printed ephemera, and third-party letters, are identified in folder notes.
Series IV, Personal Papers, housed in boxes 46-50, is organized into four suberies: Financial Records, Printed Ephemera, School Material, and Other.
The Financial Records consist chiefly of bills and receipts, though travel invoices for readings and itineraries and check stubs for readings and royalties can also be found here.
The printed material consists of clippings, conference and event materials, and ephemera, such as announcements for readings, and brochures, catalogs, and programs. The clippings document the censorship controversy surrounding Fools Crow in Montana secondary schools and French interest in The Heartsong of Charging Elk.
School Materials, which are arranged alphabetically by material type, include course papers and tests, plays and stories written for courses, and notebooks. The eighteen spiral bound notebooks, which consist chiefly of notes for various college courses, also include scattered drafts and sketches for poems and stories. Though many notebooks are undated, they appear to date from Welch's years as an undergraduate (1962-1965). Loose materials are also laid in.
Oversize material, housed in boxes 51-54, includes items from Series I and Series IV. Restricted Fragile materials are housed in box 55.
American fiction -- Indian authors; American poetry -- Indian authors; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives.; Indians of North America; Little Bighorn, Battle of the, Mont., 1876; Blackfeet Tribe of the Blackfeet Indian Reservation of Montana; Montana; Born digital.; Clippings (information artifacts); Electronic documents.; Notebooks.; Printouts.; Storage devices (computer equipment); Authors; Native American literature.; Alexie, Sherman, 1966-; Barnes, Kim; Beer, Ralph; Busch, Frederick, 1941-2006; Butala, Sharon, 1940-; Clark, LaVerne Harrell; Dillard, Annie; Erdrich, Louise; Harjo, Joy; Haruf, Kent; Henley, Patricia; Josephy, Alvin M., 1915-2005; Krupat, Arnold; Matthiessen, Peter; McFadden, Cyra; Momaday, N. Scott, 1934-; Patchett, Ann; Silko, Leslie Marmon, 1948-; Snyder, Gary, 1930-; Welch, James, 1940-2003
- Writings, 1889-2000; Series I; 13.35; (32 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Writings, is arranged into six subseries: Articles and Essays, Lectures, Novels, Poetry, Short Fiction, and Other.
  - ARTICLES AND ESSAYS
    - "A.B. Guthrie, Jr.," computer printout, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Alive and Well," computer printout, [1998 Mar 9] (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Dana Boussard," computer printout
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Correspondence, Big Sky Journal, Box 36, folder 524
    - "Enfin, le vent du renouveau," printed version, Geo, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Far North People," computer printout, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Foreword," computer printout, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Forward," draft, typescript, corrected, and typescript photocopy (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "If a Lion Could Talk," computer printout, [1995 Jan 19] (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Indian Summer at Wounded Knee," typescript and typescript photocopy, corrected (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Introduction," computer printout, [1997 Jul 28] (Box 1, Folder 9)
      See also: Correspondence, Ken Lopez, Box 39, folder 674
    - "Introduction," computer printout, [1998 Oct 12] (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Journey to St.-Malo," computer printout, [1999 Apr 22] (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "Long Time Ago," drafts, typescript, corrected, and typescript photocopy (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "The Milk River," computer printout, [1996 Oct 29] (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "Preface," computer printout, [1996 May 7] (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - "Preface," computer printout, [1999 Jan 21] (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - "Native American Renaissance," printed version, Modernization and Cultural Identity, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - ["September is like..."] draft, computer printout, corrected, and computer printout, photocopy (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "The West from Two Perspectives," computer printout, photocopy
      See: Correspondence, Rick Newby, Box 41, folder 728
    - "Writing Montana," computer printout, [1997 Feb] (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "A Young Writer's Foreign Adventures," computer printout, [1995 Nov 10] (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - "You're in Blackfeet Country," drafts, typescript, corrected, and typescript photocopy (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - LECTURES
    - "American Destiny," typescript, corrected, and holograph (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "Commencement -- Browning," draft, computer printout, corrected, 1993 Jun (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - "Fiction and Politics," computer printout, [1998 Nov 3] (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - ["For many years..."], draft, computer printout, 1990 Sep (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - ["Good evening, ladies and..."], computer printout (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - "Graduation Speech," computer printouts, [1997] (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - "The Last Stand," drafts, computer printout, corrected (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - "Native American Renaissance," computer printout, [1999 Apr 3] (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - NOVELS
    - Death of Jim Loney
      - Notes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 29)
      - [First] draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - [Second] draft, typescript and typescript photocopy, corrected (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - [Third] draft, typescript and typescript photocopy, corrected (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - [Third] draft, typescript photocopy, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 33-34)
        Includes letter to Welch from Ted Solotaroff of Bantam Books
      - [Final] draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - [Final] draft, typescript photocopy, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 36-37)
      - [Final] draft, typescript photocopy and typescript, corrected, with proofreaders' marks and printer's annotations (Box 3, Folder 38-39)
      - Miscellaneous draft pages, typescript and typescript photocopy (Box 3, Folder 40)
      - Page proofs, 1979 May (Box 4, Folder 41-42)
      - Page proofs, photocopy, with proofreaders' marks, 1979 May (Box 4, Folder 43)
      - Confirmation page proofs, 1979 Jun 27 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Fools Crow
      - Notes, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 45)
      - [First] draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 46-48)
      - [First] draft (incomplete), typescript, corrected, photocopy, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 49-50)
      - Draft, typescript, corrected, photocopy, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 51-52)
      - Drafts, typescript photocopy, corrected by William Bevis, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 53-55)
      - Draft, typescript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 56-58)
      - Draft, typescript photocopy, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 59-61)
      - Draft fragments, typescript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 62)
      - Comments by William Bevis, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 63)
      - Comments by Lois Welch, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 64)
      - Draft, computer printout, corrected, with proofreaders' marks and printer's annotations (Box 7, Folder 65-67)
        Includes letter to Welch, dated 1987, from Viking Penguin
      - Galley proof, photocopy, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 68-70)
      - Map proof, photocopy, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 71)
        Includes letter to Welch, dated 1986, from Gerald Howard of Viking Penguin
    - The Heartsong of Charging Elk
      - Synopsis, 1995-1998, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 72)
      - Background material, 1889-1993, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 73-76)
      - Notes, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 77-83)
      - Draft "One" (incomplete), computer printout, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 84)
      - Draft "Two" (incomplete), computer printout, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 85)
      - Draft, Chapters 1-2, electronic, 1995 May 18 (Box 9, Folder 86)
        Available through Access Services: Disk#21; The Marseille Grace, A Novel, Excerpt, James Welch
      - Draft, electronic, 1996-1997 (Box 9, Folder 87)
        Available through Access Services: Disk#26; French Novel Two
      - Draft, electronic, 1996-1997 (Box 9, Folder 88)
        Available through Access Services: Disk#19; French Novel One
      - [Third] draft, computer printout, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 89-90)
      - Draft, electronic, 1997 Jul (Box 9, Folder 91)
        Available through Access Services: Disk#10; Marseille Grace, 1st Version of Heartsong
      - Draft, computer printout, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 92-93)
      - Draft, Chapters 1-3, electronic, 1998 Feb (Box 9, Folder 94)
        Available through Access Services: Disk#25; French Novel 2
      - Draft, Chapters 1-9, electronic, 1998-1999 (Box 9, Folder 95)
        Available through Access Services: Disk#24; Marseille Grace #2
      - Draft, Chapters 1-13, electronic, 1998-1999 (Box 9, Folder 96)
        Available through Access Services: Disk#04; French Novel 2
      - Draft, Chapters 1-17, electronic, 1998-1999 (Box 9, Folder 97)
        Available through Access Services: Disk#20; French Novel 2, Incomplete
      - Draft, Chapters 1-17, electronic, 1998-1999 (Box 9, Folder 98)
        Available through Access Services: Disk#23, French Novel 2, Marseille Grace
      - Draft, Chapters 1-19, electronic, 1998-1999 (Box 9, Folder 99)
        Available through Access Services: Disk#01; French Novel 2, Best Copy, 19 Complete Chapters
      - Draft, computer printout, corrected, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 100-102)
      - Draft, electronic, 1998-1999 (Box 10, Folder 103)
        Available through Access Services: Disk#18; French Novel 2, Best Copy, 20 Complete, 1/2 of 21
      - Draft, computer printout, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 104-106)
      - Draft, computer printout, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 107-109)
      - Draft, Chapter 21, electronic, 1999 Oct 14 (Box 11, Folder 110)
        Available through Access Services: Disk#16; [No label]
      - Draft, computer printout, corrected by Gerald Howard, 1999 (Box 11, Folder 111-113)
      - Draft, electronic, 1998-1999 (Box 11, Folder 114)
        Available through Access Services: Disk#22; The Heartsong of Charging Elk, Gerry-edited version, 10/25/99
      - Draft, computer printout, 1999 Oct 22 (Box 12, Folder 115-117)
      - Draft, electronic, 1999 Oct (Box 12, Folder 118)
        Available through Access Services: Disk#09; French Novel
      - Draft, electronic, 1999 Oct (Box 12, Folder 119)
        Available through Access Services: Disk#12; French Novel 2
      - [Loose] drafts, computer printouts, corrected, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 120-126)
      - Drafts, computer printouts, with proofreaders' marks and printer's annotations, 1999 Nov 29 (Box 14, Folder 127-129)
      - Setting copy, corrected, 2000 Jan 27 (Box 15, Folder 130-132)
      - Setting copy, with proofreaders' marks and printer's annotations, 2000 (Box 15, Folder 133-135)
      - Reproductions of book covers, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 136)
      - Excerpt, printed version, Fiction for the Rest of Us, 2000 (Box 16, Folder 137)
      - Excerpt, printed version, The World & I, 2001 Jan (Box 16, Folder 138)
      - Publicity, 2000 (Box 16, Folder 139)
    - The Indian Lawyer
      - Notes, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 140)
      - Book proposal, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 141)
      - [Earlier] draft (incomplete), electronic, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 142)
        Available through Access Services: Disk#02; Indian Lawyer Backup
      - [Earlier] draft, electronic, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 143)
        Available through Access Services: Disk#03; Indian Lawyer 3 Backup
      - [Earlier] draft, Chapters 1-2, computer printout, corrected, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 144)
      - First draft, computer printout, corrected, [1989?] (Box 17, Folder 145-146)
      - First draft, computer printout, corrected by Gerald Howard, 1989 (Box 17, Folder 147-148)
        Includes letter from Howard dated November 29, 1989
      - Second draft, computer printout, 1989 Dec 29 (Box 18, Folder 149-150)
      - Second draft, electronic, 1989 Dec 30 (Box 18, Folder 151)
        Available through Access Services: Disk#07; Indian Lawyer Revised, 12/30/89, 2nd Version
      - Second draft, electronic, 1989 Dec 30 (Box 18, Folder 152)
        Available through Access Services: Disk#13; Indian Lawyer 1, Revised, 12/30/89, 2nd Version
      - Second draft, computer printout photocopy, corrected, 1990 Jan 5 (Box 18, Folder 153-154)
      - Drafts, Chapters 10-11, computer printouts, corrected, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 155)
      - [Final] draft, computer printout, corrected, with proofreaders' marks and printer's annotations, 1990 (Box 18, Folder 156-157)
      - Proof, Master Set, 1st Pass, corrected, with proofreaders' marks and printer's annotations, 1990 Apr 17 (Box 19, Folder 158-160)
      - Proof, Master Set, 2nd Pass, corrected, with proofreaders' marks and printer's annotations, 1990 Jun 7 (Box 19, Folder 161-163)
      - Proof, Master Set, Confirmation, 1990 Jun (Box 20, Folder 164-166)
      - Book cover (Penguin ed.), [1991] (Box 20, Folder 167)
    - Winter in the Blood
      - Abstract, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 168)
      - Character sketches, typescript and typescript photocopy (Box 21, Folder 169)
      - [Early] draft, typescript, corrected, photocopy, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 170)
      - Draft, typescript photocopy, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 171)
      - [First] draft (incomplete) typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 172)
      - [Second] draft, typescript, corrected (Box 21, Folder 173)
      - [Third] draft, typescript photocopy, corrected, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 174)
      - [Fourth] draft, typescript, typescript photocopy, and holograph, corrected (Box 21, Folder 175)
      - [Fifth] draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 176)
      - Draft, typescript photocopy and typescript, corrected (Box 22, Folder 177)
        Includes letter to Welch, dated 1974, from Ted Solotaroff of The American Review
      - Setting copy, typescript, with proofreaders' marks and printer's annotations (Box 22, Folder 178)
      - Printer's proof, with proofreaders' marks (Harper & Row ed.), 1974
      - Galley proof (Harper & Row ed.), 1974
      - Page proofs (Harper & Row ed.), [1974] (Box 22, Folder 179)
      - Drafts, jacket copy, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 180)
      - First proof, jacket copy (Harper & Row ed), 1974 Aug 15
      - Blues, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 181)
      - Drafts, film treatment, typescript, corrected, and typescript photocopy (Box 22, Folder 182)
      - Outline for screenplay, computer printout, corrected, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 183)
      - Draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 184)
      - "Dead file" material, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 185)
      - Book cover (Penguin ed.), [1986] (Box 22, Folder 186)
  - POETRY
    - Collections
      Riding the Earthboy 40
      - [Original] draft, typescript, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 187)
      - [Second] draft, typescript and typescript carbon, corrected (Box 23, Folder 188)
      - Draft, typescript photocopy, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 189)
      - Draft, typescript photocopy, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 190)
      - Draft, typescript photocopy, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 191)
      - Table of contents, draft, typescript photocopy, corrected, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 192)